hey what's up guys My Name Is AO and
welcome back to my C++ series over the
last couple of episodes we took a look
at what the static keyword meant in
certain contexts and today we're going
to have a look at one other context that
you might find the static keyword in and
that is in a local scope so you can
actually use static in a local scope to
declare a variable and that has a bit of
a different meaning than the other two
Statics that we've looked at and the
idea behind this meaning makes a lot
more sense if you think about the two
kind of considerations we have to make
when we're declaring a variable and that
is the lifetime of the variable and the
scope of the variable the lifetime
refers to how long that variable will
actually stick around for in other words
how long it will remain in our memory
before it gets deleted and then the
scope refers to where we can actually
access that variable so of course if we
declare a variable inside a function for
example we can't just access it in
another function because the variable we
declared is going to be local to the
function we declared it in so a static
local variable allows us to declare a
variable that has the lifetime of
essentially our entire program
however its scope is limited to be
inside that function and this really has
nothing to do with functions in
particular I mean you can declare this
in any scope really I'm just using
function as an example it's not really
just limited to being inside a function
could be inside an if statement could be
anywhere which is why again there's not
much of a difference between static in a
function scope versus static in a class
scope because the lifetime is actually
going to be the same the only difference
is that the one in the class scope
anything in the class can access it
anything that has anything that is
inside that class scope can access that
static variable however of course if you
declare one inside a function scope it's
going to be local to that function
instead of being local to that class
let's jump in and take a look at some
examples so the simplest example is
going to be just to create a function
and then declare some kind of static
variable inside it so I'll just make
static in I equals z what this means is
that when I call function for the first
time this variable will be initialized
to zero and then on subsequent calls to
functions it's not actually going to
create a brand new variable really easy
way to check this out is if I just print
the value of I and then I increment it
every time I call the function so if we
didn't have static here what you would
expect is that every time you call this
function I gets set to zero then I gets
incremented to one and then we print one
to the console and in fact we can test
that out by just calling function a
whole bunch of times here we'll call it
five times we'll hit our five to run our
program and you can see that we get one
printing five times because as I just
explained we create a variable every
single time and we set it equal to zero
we then increment it to one and then we
print that to the console now if we were
to make this static then it's very very
similar to if we had just moved this
original declaration out here so if we
run this code and it doesn't really
matter if this has static or not in our
case it's going to be the same if you
want to know more about what static does
in that sense you can check out the
video that's linked somewhere so if I
run this code you would expect I to be
zero increment Ed five times and so
you'll get 1 2 3 4 5 which is exactly
what you get however the problem with
this approach is that I can access I
anywhere I could set I equal to 10 over
here in between function calls and
suddenly this dramatically changes what
my program does so for cases where you
want this kind of behavior however you
do not want to give everyone access to
that variable you can declare static in
a local scope so let's get rid of this
and move our I variable back into the
function scope
I'm going to stick static out the front
which means that again the first time we
we run this function it's going to set
it equal to zero and create the variable
in the first place then on subsequent
times it's just going to refer to that
original variable so if I run my code
now you can see I get 1 2 3 4 5 and I
get the exact same behavior as I did
before however that I variable isn't
visible in a global scope it's just
local to that function now as for uses
some people do like to discourage the
use of this because of certain reasons
that I don't fully understand because I
don't really see a problem with this it
definitely has its use it's one of those
things where yes you can achieve the
exact same behavior using other methods
however that can also be said for
classes you don't necessarily have to
use classes at all to write a program
however it does make your life easier
same with this case it's one of those
things that you can just do to keep your
code a little bit cleaner another
example might be if you had a Singleton
class so a Singleton class is a class
that should only have one instance in
existence if I wanted to create this
Singleton class without using this
static local scope thing I would have to
create some kind of static Singleton
instance probably a pointer at this rate
I'll set it here I would have to have a
if I just wanted to return a normal
reference I would have to have a
Singleton reference returning get
function which was static and returned
my instance after dereferencing it of
course I would then have to actually
declare this instance over here
Singleton Singleton as instance and we
can probably set it equal to non pointer
as a default and now I have the ability
let's get rid of this now of course I
have my Singleton class in which I can
just call Singleton get and then do
whatever I want with it so suppose we
had a method here called hello don't
really know what I'm doing just an
example we could call that hello method
and everything will be well you can see
we've only got one instance of that
class that we can use so we can kind of
use it statically now this is quite a
lot of code you don't necessarily have
to do it this way another way to do this
with our new found knowledge of this
local static thing might be like this we
can get rid of this entirely we can get
rid of this external definition of s
instance as well and then we can just
expand our get function to actually
create a static Singleton instance and
then return that
instance and there you go we get the
exact same behavior you can see
everything here stays the same we can
run our code no problem of course the
code is not actually going to do
anything anything at this point but you
can see it run successfully without
crashing and we don't really have any
problems with this at all and you can
see that our code is a lot lot cleaner
now of course if you didn't have the
static keyword here then this Singleton
since it is just created on the stack
would get destroyed as soon as you hit
this curly bracket and and then the
function scope ends so this would be a
grave error especially if you're
returning it by reference if you're
copying it of course you wouldn't really
have a problem however since we are
returning a reference to it this would
would be a huge problem however by
adding static where extending the
lifetime of this to be essentially
forever which means that every time we
call get the first time it will actually
construct that Singleton instance then
on all subsequent times it will just
return that existing instance so this is
a great example of where you might want
to use something like this it doesn't
necessarily have to be with Singletons
it can help you out a lot by replacing
initialization functions where for
example you might have to call a static
initial where for example you might have
to call a static initialization function
at some point in your program to create
all of your objects so that you could
actually use the static get methods and
stuff like that you can just kind of
simplify that by using this in a lot of
cases so you can see there are tons of
uses for this and it's really not all
that bad so feel free to use it that's
my opinion let me know what you guys
think of this static in a local scope
thing in the comments below and I'll see
you guys in the next video
[Music]
goodbye
he